In this video, we will be talking about
how
matter can behave like waves.
Now we know waves can behave like matter,
because
light behaves like matter.
Light is a particle, a photon. So that
raises
the question, then if everything is
matter,
and if this type of matter behaves like
waves,
then can all types of matter behave like
waves?
Well, modern physics actually shows that
it
can. Now a scientist about 100 years ago
proposed
that if photons can behave like particles,
then
these particles should all have wavelength
and
behave like waves. And he proposed that
the
wavelength of the particles is equal to
Planck's
constant over momentum, or Planck's
constant
over matter. And this equation is actually
later
proven to be true. And this applies for
all
types of matter. For example, it applies
to
you right now. The atoms that make you up
are
actually vibrating or oscillating and
behaving
like waves. And although it may not seem
like
it, if you look at your hand, it's pretty
solid,
it's not vibrating. That's because your
wavelength
is really really really small.
Planck's constant, h, is about 6.63 times
to the negative 34 metres squared
kilograms
per second. So if the numerator is this
small,
then there is a really really good chance
that
you won't be able to notice anything.
But that's the rule out there, and
everything
behaves like waves. And this was very
controversial
when it first came out, because in
classical
physics, mass behaved like a particle, and
no
mass behaved like a wave. And this
scientist
unified both. So he proposed this formula,
which
basically proves that everything has both
wave
and particle properties.
So when we talk about wave-particle
duality
about light, this actually applies for
everything.
All of us and every type of matter
undergoes
wave-particle duality. And like I said,
it's
only noticeable for very very small
electrons.
It must have an extremely small mass or
speed
for this to actually be non-negligible,
for
example electrons. But if you're looking
at
a baseball, this basically is
non-existent.
So the experimental proof for this was
electron
diffraction. I have talked about this in
another
unit, so I'm not going to go over it. But
basically
it proved that light behaves like a wave.
And that basically also changed a lot of
what
we know. Before we were using the
Bohr-Rotherford
diagram, which is discrete energy levels
and
electrons go around it. Well now we know
that
electrons or any subatomic particle has a
relatively
non-negligible wave, then how does that
work?
Well, we used quantized energy level.
And this is going a bit into chemistry,
but
I'll quickly brief you about it.
We divide things into subatomic orbitals.
And orbitals are direct paths. Orbitals
are
clouds or a place of possibilities of
where
the electron can be, because the electron
is
going up and down and behaving like a
wave.
So it's nearly impossible to predict where
exactly
the electron is. So orbitals basically are
estimations
of where the electron is likely to be
clustered.
And yeah, that's basically it for this
video.
And I hope you learned something. We'll
see
you in the next one about the limits of
possible
measurements since we now know about this
wave
particle duality, and why exactly position
and
momentum can't both be known.
So yeah, that's it for today's video and
we'll
see you in the next one. Thank you!